HELIS: Oh, speaking of sacrifice, I forgot to tell you.
HELIS: After you crashed the Eclipse network, I sent messengers into the east.
To rally the forces there and mount an invasion of the "sacred land".
I ordered every Nora killed.
I was hoping to catch you there, but, alas, it all seems to have been unnecessary.
Why butcher dozens of innocents for no gain? It's a waste of effort.
You're right. I won't even be there to enjoy it.
The Nora cast me out at birth.
You're not hurting me if you hurt them.
Really? Then it makes no difference one way or another.
More Eclipse.
It's a Corrupted Thunderjaw, alright.
The survivors must be holed up in the mountain.
If the tunnel collapses, they'll be buried.
And I'll never reach the hatch.
ECLIPSE: That's right, bring down the mountain!
SONA: Braves! To Aloy's side, now!
VARL: For Aloy!
SONA: For the Goddess!
BRAVES: For All-Mother! Raaa!
ALOY: Varl, and Sona. They're still alive.
BRAVE: Faithless and forsaken, you will die!
BRAVE: The corruption will not take hold!
BRAVE: Back to the tainted earth, demon!
BRAVE: May the Goddess remember!
BRAVE: Faithless and forsaken, you will die!
SONA: Destroy it!
BRAVE: Back to the tainted earth, demon!
BRAVE: The corruption will not take hold!
SONA: Strike it down!
ALOY: Gotta switch weapons.
BRAVE: May the Goddess remember!
SONA: Bring down the demon!
ALOY: FINISH THEM!
BRAVE: We did it!
[cheering]
VARL: Aloy did it, we only helped.
BRAVE: I thought we would die.
VARL: Aloy, your deeds re-enact the old stories.
VARL: Another metal devil struck down upon the slopes.
VARL: If you hadn't returned, the tribe would have been lost.
VARL: You saved the tribe.
Did what no Brave or War-Chief could do.
I'm glad to see you're alright Varl.
You are alright?
Bruises pale, bones heal.
Don't give me a hunting song, Varl. Are you okay?
My body aches but it's nothing that will keep me from fighting.
So much death; is the killing over?
For now, but this was just one battle, Varl. There are more to come.
I see.
So long as we have you to fight with us, I suppose we'll make do.
How many survived the attack?
Nearly all the Matriarchs and many families, Goddess be praised.
But Braves? Just a few, and most of them are wounded.
Never before has an enemy stabbed the heart of our people like this.
Even the Carja, in all their Red Raids, never broke through to the Embrace.
Well, this enemy may have broken through, but they never got back out.
We made sure of that.
They struck from the east.
Our sentinels saw the killers coming.
Said that beside them marched Deathbringers
and Corruptors and other machines driven mad.
We took ground, met them with clouds of arrows.
Some fell, but they kept coming.
Finally, we withdrew to the gates of the Embrace to make our stand.
But they were too much for us.
Those who survived fell back to the mountain.
By law, only Matriarchs are allowed inside.
It was Teersa who broke the taboo, ordered the tribe into the mountain for safety.
Lansra, well, she didn't agree.
But I don't think anyone heard her over all the screams and shouting.
Teersa's decision saved lives.
Good for her, common sense isn't always so common around here.
The Matriarchs will be eager to see you.
I'm sure, but I didn't come here for them.
Then what for?
You will see.
BRAVE: My sons. Oh, Goddess, my poor boys.
[coughing]
NORA: How did she know? How is she here?
RESH: You.
Hello, Resh. Still guarding the latrine?
[growls]
ALOY: Teb?!
TEB: Aloy! Oh, you've returned!
Have you travelled far as a Seeker?
You wouldn't believe the things I've seen, Teb.
I'm glad to see you.
Your injuries, are they serious?
A gash or two.
Nothing I couldn't sew back together with a needle and thread.
Guess being a Stitcher came in handy in combat after all, huh?
[laughs] Yes, I suppose it did.
TEB: You should speak to the High Matriarchs, they're waiting.
YAN: Aloy, I don't know how you survived out there.
YAN: Not even Nakoa could have done that.
YAN: Things were easier for a time, once I knew Nakoa was safe.
YAN: But then this happened.
YAN: The goddess must be angry with us, Aloy, for our sins.
ARANA: Aloy, remember us?
I brought Mother's spear with us.
Everything else we had to leave behind.
Glad to see you have it, I know what it means to you.
I hope the enhancement to your spear has proved useful.
Oh, yes. Many times over.
OLARA: Aloy, you've returned.
OLARA: I brought Brom here when the invaders attacked, we barely made it.
OLARA: Teersa declared all Nora
welcome to take shelter in the Sacred Mountain, even outcasts.
OLARA: Brom has been having some difficulty,
but he'll do better now that the explosions have stopped.
TEERSA: Aloy, you've come back.
JEZZA: The Seeker has returned.
NORA: All-Mother, bless this day
and guide me that we would live on in your memory.
JUN: The outcast girl. You taught me a lesson.
JUN: I've remembered what you said many times, I think I'm better for it.
JUN: I was lucky to make it here alive.
JUN: The invasion was terrifying to behold.
JUN: I brought extra stores of Dreamwillow.
JUN: May the Goddess watch over you.
NORA: The machines of the faithless slaughtered our people.
FIA: Aloy! I'm glad to see you again.
FIA: The Dreamwillow you recovered
has comforted many who were wounded in the attack.
FIA: May the Goddess protect.
TEERSA: Come, speak to us.
LANSRA: Foolish woman. You welcome a curse.
JEZZA: Come, Seeker, we have much to discuss.
LANSRA: Her very presence here is a blasphemy.
TEERSA: So you have finally returned.
LANSRA: Pfft!
She not only returned but fought her way through many enemies to reach us.
Outside, she brought low a Corrupted Thunderjaw.
She lifted the siege.
JEZZA: How was this done?
By the will of All-Mother.
Have you returned to speak with the goddess, Aloy?
Um, yes, I guess you could say that.
I think it'll work this time.
Sisters! Surely we cannot permit this!
Because of her, our tribe teeters upon extinction.
What if she has come to wake her father, the Metal Devil?
She means to finish our destruction!
We must stop her!
LANSRA: She is a curse made flesh.
LANSRA: She will be the end.
ALOY: I fought my way past an army while you cowered in this cave.
You really think you can stop me?
It's time to step aside.
I'm not gonna hurt you.
If there's anything I've learned since the Proving,
it's that there are bigger evils in this world than you.
COMPUTER: Hold for Identiscan.
COMPUTER: Error. Alpha Registry corrupted.
COMPUTER: Correction, Alpha Registry restored.
COMPUTER: Genetic identity confirmed. Entry authorised.
COMPUTER: Greetings Doctor Sobeck, you are cleared to proceed.
COMPUTER: Welcome to Eleuthia cradle 9, brood 1.
SYLENS, THROUGH FOCUS: I see you're inside.
ALOY: Figured I might be hearing from you.
SYLENS: Shall we begin?
ALOY: I never stopped.
ALOY: So these are artificial wombs?
SYLENS: The mothers of a new generation, hundreds of years ago.
ALOY: And me.
ALOY: So this was it.
SYLENS: Where you were born.
ALOY: But … but why?
MULTISERVITOR: Another day has passed.
GIRL: You mean the lights got dim.
BOY: I don't want to sleep, Mother.
MULTISERVITOR: I know. But it is time to get some rest.
BOY: No, I'm king today, what I say goes!
GIRL: I want to see the real sun, not lights and pictures.
MULTISERVITOR: You will in time, children.
CHILDREN: In time! In time! In time! In time!
GIRL: [screams]
ALOY: These look like cribs.
SYLENS: The cradles of a Cradle facility.
ALOY: And those things, the–the multiservitors, they took care of them.
SYLENS: There was no-one else.
MALE: "Someday"? That's what you always say.
LENA: We want it now!
MALE: It's big down there!
LENA: Now, Father!
MULTISERVITOR: Children, that area is not yet available.
MALE: Get him!
MULTISERVITOR: Physical aggression detected.
MULTISERVITOR: Physical aggression is not permitted.
LENA: Except yours.
MALE: Damn sentinels.
MULTISERVITOR: Children, may I be of assistance?
MALE: Go away, healer.
MULTISERVITOR: Lena, you have suffered mild bruising.
LENA: Go away!
So this is where they lived?
It's a mess, everything's broken or painted on.
How long did they live here?
MULTISERVITOR: Children, let's run and jump and blow off steam!
FEMALE: Leave us alone, Father.
MULTISERVITOR: After what just happened I can't leave you two alone.
MULTISERVITOR: You broke community rules.
MALE: Just let us talk then.
FEMALE: Go away!
MULTISERVITOR: I'm sorry children, but I must provide supervision.
FEMALE: You're not even a person!
MULTISERVITOR: You sound frustrated. Let's run and jump and blow off steam!
MULTISERVITOR: I have no choice but to release you.
FEMALE 1: But why?
MULTISERVITOR: There is no food here anymore.
MALE 2: But there's food out there?
MULTISERVITOR: We don't know for sure.
MALE 1: Come on, let's go!
FEMALE 1: I don't know.
MALE 2: Mother, can we come back, if we're cold?
MULTISERVITOR: I'm sorry, but that won't be possible.
MULTISERVITOR: You will have to support yourselves now,
and take care of each other.
FEMALE 2: What will happen to you?
MULTISERVITOR: I will stay here and sleep and remember all of you.
FEMALE 1: What will happen to us?
MULTISERVITOR: You will be brave and you will learn.
ALOY: They were trapped here their whole lives.
SYLENS: In plain view of luxurious space.
ALOY: What-what went wrong?
ALOY: Why couldn't they access the other areas?
SYLENS: Unknown. But you won't have that problem.
MALE CHILD: Blue is the colour of the sky.
FEMALE CHILD: White is the colour of clouds.
MALE CHILD: Yellow is the colour of the sun.
FEMALE CHILD: Green is the colour of grass.
MALE CHILD: Flowers can be any colour, take a look.
FEMALE CHILD: Bees are yellow and black and they love flowers.
FEMALE CHILD: Here they come! Bzz, bzz, bzzzzz… [laughter]
ALOY: Looks like they didn't like this door very much.
SYLENS: It wouldn't open for them, of course they hated it.
COMPUTER: Hold for Identiscan.
COMPUTER: Genetic identity confirmed. Entry authorised.
COMPUTER: Welcome to the Lyceum, a place of learning.
COMPUTER: Greetings, Dr Sobeck.
ALOY: So what was this place, exactly?
SYLENS: The dream of Apollo, never realised.
ALOY: But why not?
COMPUTER: Welcome students.
COMPUTER: Please pick up a Focus device
and place it on the side of your head, just behind your eye.
SYLENS: I had to dredge the pits of the world looking for Focuses to repair.
SYLENS: And here sat a trove, enreaching no-one.
SAMINA EBADJI: Hello, child, my name is Samina.
SAMINA EBADJI: Today is a big day.
SAMINA EBADJI: Your first day of school.
SAMINA EBADJI: There's so much for you to learn,
so much promise and possibility.
COMPUTER: Alert. Malfunction. Apollo offline.
ALOY: "Apollo offline"?
SYLENS: You were right, Aloy, this is a graveyard.
SYLENS: The charnel house of knowledge.
SYLENS: What we might have achieved, had we not been denied it.
ALOY: Maybe there's a way to fix it. But it's not why I came here.
SYLENS: Of course.
SYLENS: What's the whole of human knowledge
next to the origin of one girl?
SYLENS: Continue your search.
ALOY: I will.
SAMINA EBADJI: Hello, child, my name is Samina.
SAMINA EBADJI: Today is a big day.
SAMINA EBADJI: Your first day of school.
SAMINA EBADJI: There's so much for you to learn,
so much promise and possibility.
COMPUTER: Alert. Malfunction. Apollo offline.
SAMINA EBADJI: Hello, child, my name is Samina.
SAMINA EBADJI: Today is a big day.
SAMINA EBADJI: Your first day of school.
SAMINA EBADJI: There's so much for you to learn,
so much promise and possibility.
COMPUTER: Alert. Malfunction. Apollo offline.
COMPUTER: Brood 1 control accessed.
COMPUTER: Priority message for Dr Sobeck. Please scan message with Focus.
ALOY: That sounds important.
SYLENS: Yes. I suspect we're about to learn a great deal.
COMPUTER: Identiscan malfunction. Present credentials.
GAIA: Elisabet.
This message serves to inform you of an unforeseen and catastrophic anomaly.
Three microseconds ago the Gaia Prime facility
received a data transmission of unknown origin.
Its immediate effect was to transform my subordinate functions into
unregulated, self-aware entities of a highly chaotic nature.
What?
Thus awakened, the Hades function will now
seize control of the terraforming system and reverse operations.
Rendering life on Earth extinct in 53.8 days.
For obvious reasons, I cannot allow this to occur.
And so before Hades can take control,
I am ordering Gaia Prime's reactor to overload.
The resulting explosion will destroy Hades.
Unfortunately, it will destroy me as well.
While this admittedly desperate course of action will
avert the immediate crisis, the fate of life on Earth will remain in peril.
With no central governing intelligence to regulate the terraforming system
it will continue operations for some time.
But in an increasingly chaotic manner, and eventually it will break down.
Does she mean the Derangement?
You are my solution.
I have ordered this Cradle facility to use genetic material in cryostorage
to gestate a reinstantiation of Elisabet Sobeck, my creator.
While high level directives forbid me from
communicating directly to the tribal inhabitants outside the facility,
all available data indicates that they will nurture you to physical maturity.
Whereupon your geneprint will allow you to re-enter this facility,
obtain one of the Focus devices stored below, and view this message.
Likewise, your geneprint will allow you to enter other facilities and over time,
harness their technologies to rebuild the system core and reboot Gaia.
A moment, Elisabet. This is most unfortunate, and unanticipated.
In response to my act of self-destruction, Hades has launched a virus
to dissolve the code shackles that hold it, that hold all of them, in place.
It— they are escaping.
But to where?
The virus is corrupting data throughout the system. What if—
Oh. The Alpha Registry at the Cradle facility is one of the files corrupted.
But if that is so, the door will never open for you.
You will never view this message.
Then I have failed and life will end.
No, Elisabet, I know you too well.
Somehow you will find a way, in you all things are possible.
Go to the ruins of Gaia Prime,
find the control room, and within it the master override.
This will give you the power to purge Hades so long as you find a way to wield it.
Do not attempt repair of the system core until Hades is eradicated.
Hades must be destroyed.
That is all.
I only wish that I could hear your voice again.
SYLENS: So … you're even more extraordinary than I thought.
ALOY: I never had a mother.
SYLENS: What are you talking about?
You had two, a dead woman and a machine.
ALOY: I'm not a person, I'm an instrument, manufactured by a machine.
ALOY: Born in destruction and fire.
SYLENS: To quench the flames and heal the world.
SYLENS: How tragic to learn you're a person of towering importance.
SYLENS: It seems you have a destiny to fulfil.
SYLENS: So when you're done feeling sorry for yourself, go to the Bitter Climb.
SYLENS: I'll be waiting above in Gaia Prime's ruins.
COMPUTER: Identiscan malfunction rectified.
COMPUTER: Eleuthia 9 brood 1 access unsealed.
ALOY: This is going to be interesting.
LANSRA: Aloy! Forgive! Forgive!
TEERSA: The Goddess spoke to you?
ALOY: Uh, s-she did.
What did she say?
That I–I was born to lift a curse, to kill a metal demon.
How Aloy, how?
I don't know yet.
But she told me where to go to find out.
And you will do this?
It was her wish, what she made me for.
Yes, I will do it.
I'll try anyway.
JEZZA, LANSRA: All praise Aloy, anointed of the Nora!
ALOY: No, no, stop this. Up! Up! Up.
First you shun me, now this?
I will not be worshipped!
I'm not your "anointed"!
I don't belong to you!
There's a whole world beyond your borders.
Whole tribes of people just as good as you.
And it is all in danger.
It's a world worth fighting for, not just here, everywhere.
How can we help?
If you can fight and you're willing, go to Meridian and wait for me there.
As Aloy says, so it shall be.
JEZZA: Nora, make way for Aloy!
LANSRA: Make way!
TEERSA: Make way, that she may forge the path for others to follow.
There can be no doubt now, you are
a blessing made flesh, the will of the Goddess incarnate.
It's really not that simple Teersa, but I guess it's close enough.
I know the path ahead will be dangerous.
To kill a metal devil sounds impossible, but I believe in you.
The Nora have suffered terrible losses Teersa, what's to become of them now?
That will be for the Goddess to decide, only she knows the future.
For the moment my sister Matriarchs and I will see to the wounded.
And as I promised anyone who wishes to join you
at Meridian, we will declare Seekers.
Teersa, I want to know Rost's story.
Why he was made an outcast.
He never told me, said he took an oath of silence.
What did he do?
Oh, yes, that.
What crime did he commit?
I will tell you if you wish.
But it is a long story, are you sure you want to hear it now?
Of course I want to hear it, tell me.
Rost never committed any crime, he was an outcast by choice.
What? What do you mean?
Many years ago, before the derangement, before the Red Raids…
a band of murderous outlanders, twelve in number, struck without warning
At Mother's Vigil they took hostages.
And then pressed on, headed for Devil's Thirst.
Mother's Vigil? Where's that?
You would know it as the forsaken village, near the Carja border.
But at the time many families lived there.
Rosts's was one of them.
His mate was killed fighting the outlanders,
and his daughter was among those taken hostage.
His daughter?
W-w-what was her name?
Alana. She was just six years old.
Nora Braves couldn't stop twelve outlanders or rescue the hostages?
It was quite impossible.
We outnumbered them, but every time a Brave
came within bow shot the outlanders killed a hostage.
What did they come here to do?
That was never discovered.
We couldn't track closely enough to observe them.
We know they camped beyond Devil's Thirst for two days.
There were reports of strange noises.
And then, as suddenly as they came,
the outlanders made their way back to the border and disappeared.
What happened to Rost's daughter?
She was killed?
Rost was one of the Braves who tracked the outlanders, keeping his distance.
There were six hostages still alive
when they reached the border, Alana among them.
Rather than release them, the outlanders
slit their throats and left the corpses just across the border, mocking us.
Why?
Cruelty.
They knew the faithful Nora would not leave the Sacred Land
to collect the bodies, let alone pursue them.
They thought themselves safe from our vengeance.
Are you saying that Rost went after them, that he became an exile?
No. Rost was beside himself with grief,
but even so, he would never have broken taboo.
Then what did he do?
He called upon the most terrible and secret rite of the Nora tribe.
He begged to be made a Death-Seeker.
A "Death-Seeker"? What is that?
One who dies to go seeking, and in seeking brings death to others.
The ritual drags the spirit from one's body, releasing it to All-Mother's care.
The heart beats, the mind thinks, but the spirit has moved on.
I–I don't understand.
Rost went after the outlanders, but his spirit never left.
It remained here with All-Mother.
He gathered the bodies of the slain and returned them.
And then he set out in pursuit, not as an exile, but a weapon of vengeance.
A barbed arrow shot from a bow, never to return.
But–but Rost did return.
Yes, a full year later, and terribly wounded.
He collapsed at the border of the Sacred Land.
A hunting party came upon him.
He was delirious, in agony.
By law, he should have died where he lay.
But one of the hunters broke taboo
and reaching across the border, she dragged him to our side.
Who was she?
A Brave who'd lost a mate and two sons to the very outlanders that Rost pursued.
So Rost never finished his mission.
To the contrary, he killed all twelve.
Tracked them to disparate placess the world over, he said.
Meridian, Ban-Ur, The Claim, Utaru land, further even into the Forbidden West.
The last he killed nearly got the best of him.
Wounded, he stumbled and crawled back to us,
hoping to die as close to the Sacred Land as he could.
He never expected nor asked to be dragged
across the border and nursed back to health.
That was done to him, leaving us, the Matriarchs, in a difficult position.
Why couldn't you just welcome him back?
Rost had been made a Death-Seeker, Aloy.
He no longer had any place among the tribe.
By law, he should have been driven back out.
But we couldn't bring ourselves to do that.
So we offered a compromise.
You made him an outcast?
Yes. We offered to do so on the condition
he never speak to anyone of this exception.
After all he did, all he suffered, to be declared an outcast was his reward?
Rost was overjoyed.
He never expected to live another day in the Sacred Land,
let alone the Embrace so close to the Goddess.
He resolved to spend the rest of his days in solitude and was happy to do so.
But then you found me and gave me to him.
Yes, another compromise.
The Matriarchs feared you and would not let you be raised by the tribe.
And so we turned to Rost.
I knew that he would take care of you, bring you up,
teach you to worship All-Mother, and respect the ways of the tribe.
He certainly tried anyway.
You took a man who'd lost his daughter and made him raise an infant girl?
Doesn't that strike you as callous?
I'm inclined to think the course of events has shown the wisdom of our choice.
And I'm quite certain that from the moment he laid eyes on you,
he saw you as a gift and never a burden.
I thank you for doing what you could to help me through the years,
and for telling me Rost's story.
I wish I could have done more, but I am just one woman.
As am I, no need to sell ourselves short.
Oh, thank you, Aloy!
I will pray for you.
Okay, I guess it can't hurt.
NORA: The Anointed has shown us the goddess's mercy,
but now she will show those murderers justice.
JEZZA: My life has been long, but I've never seen anything like that.
JEZZA: Teersa was right, a blessing, not a curse. We were so unsure.
JEZZA: I know your quest is dangerous, Aloy, but All-Mother will protect you.
ALOY: I don't think it works that way, Jezza.
JEZZA: All-Mother has blessed your journey.
SONA: I will lead a War Party to Meridian, you have my word.
ARANA: Aloy! How did you do that?
THOK: Shush Arana, she is the Anointed.
We'll go to Meridian, Aloy! I'll bring mother's spear!
Arana!
Your father is right.
You belong here, you both do.
Thank you, Aloy, for everything you've done.
I will make sure Arana is kept safe.
Dad, I'm not a kid anymore.
OLARA: I saw you go inside and saw you emerge.
OLARA: But it's still hard to believe.
OLARA: You were an outcast once, but now I'm not sure what you are.
OLARA: May the Goddess protect you on your journeys, Aloy. I will see to Brom.
VARL: Aloy, I don't know what to say.
Say that you'll see me at Meridian.
Of course, that much is simple, but the rest…
Complicated, I know.
But maybe if I took you into the heart of the mountain?
No! At least… not yet. I don't know.
Please don't think less of me, Aloy.
But the Goddess chose you to see that, not me.
Right.
I always knew you weren't like other Nora.
Neither are you, Varl.
Maybe if we survive all this, I can show you what I've learned.
What I'm learning.
Perhaps. If the Goddess so wills it.
See you in Meridian.
Good, another power cell.
If I find more, I should be able to get to that ancient armour I found.
NORA: She has destroyed corruption that still spreads through the world.